Ram Kumar G Software Architect

9177802644

Hyderabad, India

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/ramkr-g

Profile

A seasoned software architect with over 11 years of experience in application development, specializing in distributed systems, scalability, and cloud-based solutions. I focus on creating systems that smoothly follow the principles of distributed computing, ensuring they scale well and operate efficiently.

Professional Experience

2021 - present

Software Architect | Platform Engineer

Descign AI LLP

- Collaborated in foundational technical architecture discussions, shaping the startup's early-stage product development and actively involved to address key challenges of a SAAS product, focusing on compliance (SOC2, HIPAA, GAMP5 etc), security, and scale
- Led the initiative to create digital workspaces, addressing daily computational needs for research activities such as data analysis on Jupyter, molecular cloning tools, primers, etc., offering a seamless experience akin to GitHub Codespaces directly within a browser

2019 - 2021

Software Architect Lead

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

- As a key contributor to platform architecture at NowFloats (JIO subsidiary), I led initiatives focused on developing and managing processes and solutions for diverse projects, serving both internal and external stakeholders
- With a focus on platform architecture, I applied expertise from web development to social media strategies, significantly improving scalability, reliability, and uptime. While my responsibilities were centered on platform architecture, the impact of my work resonated across both enterprise and small businesses
- Implemented PII, HIPAA and EHR compliance data standards across the platform

2017 - 2019

Platform Architect

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

- Developed serverless architecture on Kitsune platform for enterprises and SMBs, ensuring high availability and optimal performance
- Fostered a collaborative environment with developers, enhancing the development, testing, and deployment process via web IDE and a user-friendly dashboard
- Directed the transition from .NET Framework to .NET Core, significantly boosting performance by reducing boot times from 4 minutes to 1 minute and 20 seconds and 30% cost reduction
- Implemented a hybrid strategy, integrating a warm pool, spot instances, on-demand EC2, and Serverless Lambda to handle high traffic efficiently. This approach led to a substantial 70% cost savings across our technology stack

2015 - 2017

Software Development Lead

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

- Led a team of 20 developers, conducting daily scrum sessions and high-quality code reviews to drive continuous optimization
- Engineered and maintained scalable architectures for diverse applications, achieving 40% cost reduction. Ensured continuous operation for over 250,000 websites
- Guided the shift to a cloud-based, event-driven microservices architecture, integrating serverless and container solutions. This resulted in a 30% increase in throughput, enhancing efficiency and scalability

• Led data engineering efforts to build advanced data pipelines, significantly enhancing data analytics capabilities and optimizing database performance for improved integrity and accessibility

2014 – 2015 Senior Software Development Engineer

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

- As a Senior Software Engineer, I held a pivotal role in managing crucial aspects of software development, including the business layer, API stack, and both web and serverside applications
- Led the development and implementation of an advanced notification system, managing user communications, email deliverability, and content verification effectively

2012 – 2014 Software Development Engineer

- Developed web and server-side applications, optimizing for schema.org standards and applying SEO techniques to boost website traffic and crawl rates
- Actively participated in API stack management and performed ongoing server maintenance

Projects

ILA - Intelligent Lab Assistant

Descign AI LLP

ILA, the Intelligent Lab Assistant, transforms laboratories into R&D hubs by implementing digitization, automation, and governance. It streamlines workflow management, enhances productivity and reproducibility for researchers worldwide

Kitsune

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

Kitsune simplifies cloud application development with user-focused tools for web development, content management, and effortless construction of scalable serverless/cloud-native applications

RIA

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

RIA, the virtual web consultant, enhances user engagement by providing personalized assistance, analytics, and targeted outreach, offering a human-like interaction platform

Auto Discovery Service

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

Crafted to boost organic website discovery on NowFloats, this service optimizes the process by extracting keywords with rule-based tokenization. It automates tag generation, creating searchable backlinks, and aligns schema standards based on the relevance for business category

Platform Communication Service Layer

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

This layer effectively manages all platform communications, enhancing user engagement by optimizing email, SMS, and notification delivery. It reduces bounce rates and accurately classifies content, handling large volumes efficiently

Skills

Languages

C# (.NET Framework & Core), NodeJS, Python, Go

Search

ElasticSearch, Typesense

Queue/Streams

SQS, ServiceBus and Kinesis

MISC

Serverless Architecture, DataLake,
Container orchestration tools,

CI/CD, IaC tools (CloudFormation, Terraform)

Databases

MySQL, SQLServer, MongoDB, DynamoDB

Cache

Redis, MemCached

Cloud

Amazon Web Services (AWS) Microsoft Azure

Google Cloud Platform (GCP)

Awards

Most Valuable Person

NowFloats Technologies Pvt Ltd

Awarded as an MVP (Most Valuable Person) twice during my role as SDE and SSDE

Education

2008 – 2012 Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

Hyderabad, India DRK College Of Engineering and Technology, J.N.T University